Preliminary Guide to the Stephanie Strickland Papers, 1955-2012
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Stephanie Strickland papers 1955-2009
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Strickland, Stephanie
12.9 linear feet Extent: 5550 Items
Stephanie Strickland is a poet and born-digital writer whose works range from paper to interactive websites. She also teaches and serves on the board of the Electronic Literature Organization. The accessions include journals and anthologies featuring Strickland's poetry; TechnoPoetry Festival materials; schoolwork, college, and graduate papers; posters and programs from events; proofs and drafts of her writings; and audio recordings. A data CD-ROM has been separated from the collection for migration to Duke's electronic server.
RL.01262
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Some materials may require preservation copies be created before use.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Stephanie Strickland Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2009.
Biographical Note
Stephanie Strickland is a poet and digital writer whose works range from paper to interactive websites. She also teaches and serves on the board of the Electronic Literature Organization.
Strickland's books are among the first examples of printed text being published in conjunction with electronic media. During her career, Strickland's work has included interactive poetry CDs; hypertext disks; poems in printed journals and anthologies; and articles about literature and cyberspace.
Collection Overview
Accession (2009-0158) (200 items; 4.5 lin. ft.; dated 1979-2008) includes printed journals and anthologies featuring Strickland's poetry, as well as 1 audio CD. A data CD-ROM (Conversing with Mystery: Poetry for Transition and Loss) has been separated from the collection for migration to Duke's electronic server.
Accession (2009-0172) (700 items; 3.0 lin. ft.; dated 1950s-2009) includes programs and posters from Strickland's publications and performances; school materials from high school to graduate school; articles and anthologies; electronic media (removed); videotapes; and other miscellaneous materials.
Accession (2009-0195) (700 items; 1.2 lin. ft.; dated 1955-2008) includes files, proofs, and drafts from Strickland's V: Vniverse, True North, Zone: Zero, Red Virgin, Give the Body Back, etc., along with some high school materials, cassette tapes, and a videotape.
Accession (2009-0267) (700 items; 1.2 lin. ft.; dated 1959-2009) includes college papers and essays from her time at Harvard; source materials from works such as Zone: Zero, True North, Sand Soot, and Vniverse; conference programs; journals; and gallery catalogs and other sources used in her work.
Accession (2011-0171) (2250 items; 3.0 lin. ft.; dated 1970s-2012) includes notes, drafts and variants of works such as True North, The Red Virgin, V: WaveSon.nets/Losing L'una, and other Strickland poems, essays, and compilations. Also includes a small amount of correspondence and event material. Electronic media has been separated from the accession and housed on Duke's electronic records server.
This collection has not been processed. Materials are arranged and described as received. Consult the Collection Control File for more information about materials in Accession (2009-0172) and Accession (2009-0267).
Subject Headings
Strickland, Stephanie; Electronic Literature Organization; Hypertext poetry; Poetry, Modern -- 20th century; Poetry, Modern -- 21st century; CD-ROMs
Contents of Collection
- Accession (2009-0158), 1979-2008, (3 boxes)
  The accession (2009-0158) (200 items; 4.5 lin. ft.; dated 1979-2008) includes printed journals and anthologies featuring Strickland's poetry, as well as 1 audio CD. These journals have been listed below, with volume and date where available. A data CD-ROM (Conversing with Mystery: Poetry for Transition and Loss) has been separated from the collection for migration to Duke's electronic server.
  - Controlled Burn 1, Winter 1995 (Box 1)
  - Connecticut Review 12.1, Spring 2000 (Box 1)
  - Indiana Review 27.1, 2005 (Box 1)
  - Extended Outlooks: The Iowa Review Collection of Contemporary Women Writers, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Barrow Street 2.1, Fall 1999 (Box 1)
  - Tendril: A Poetry Magazine 13, Summer 1982 (Box 1)
  - Tendril: A Poetry Magazine 19-20 (Box 1)
  - Prairie Schooner, 1985 (2), 1987, 1990, and 1994 (Box 1)
  - West Branch 7-8, 1980 (Box 1)
  - West Branch 14, 1984 (Box 1)
  - West Branch 26, 1990 (Box 1)
  - American Letters and Commentary 5, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Voices in Italian Americana, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Ironwood 16, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Ironwood 23, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Ironwood 25, 1985 (Box 1)
  - The Agni Review 14 and 20 (Box 1)
  - Chain 5, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Ploughshares 27.1, Spring 2001 (Box 1)
  - The Paris Review 132, Fall 1994 (Box 1)
  - Tin Fish 3, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Big Allis 8, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Salt Hill 6, 1998 (Box 1)
  - State Street Reader, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Southern Poetry Review, Spring 1986 (Box 1)
  - Soundings East 8.2, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Pequod 14, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Kenyon Review 13.3, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Kenyon Review 15.4, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Kenyon Review 17.1, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Poets and Writers, 2001 (Box 1)
    Includes an article on literature and cyberspace.
  - Iris: A Journal About Women 14, 1985 (Box 1)
  - America, 15 June 1991 (Box 1)
  - The Mad Hatter's Review (online journal), 4 May 2008 (Box 1)
  - Poetry New York 12, Spring 2001 (Box 1)
  - Audio CD: Conversing with Mystery: Poetry for Transition and Loss (Box 1)
  - The Chowder Review 20/21, Summer 1985 (Box 2)
  - Seneca Review 30.2, Fall 2000 (Box 2)
  - Pomegranate Series 4, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Ploughshares 10.1, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Iowa Review 9.3, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Iowa Review 12.2-3, 1981 (Box 2)
  - New World Poetry Bi-Monthly, December 2003 (Box 2)
  - Samizdat 1, 1998 (Box 2)
  - Dark Horse 18, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Synaesthetic 2 (Box 2)
  - Boston Review 24.5, 1999 (Box 2)
  - Poetry Now 5.1, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Small Moon (Box 2)
  - Calapooya Collage 12, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Calapooya Collage 17, 1993 (Box 2)
  - The Epistolary Form and the Letter as Artifact 17, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Poets on Nourishment 9.1, Winter 1985 (Box 2)
  - Poet Love 90.3, Fall 1995 (Box 2)
  - Slant: A Journal of Poetry, Summer 1987 (Box 2)
  - Chelsea 70/71, 2001 (Box 2)
  - Porch 4.1, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
  - Isotope 4.1, 2006 (Box 2)
    Includes an article on poetry and science.
  - Calyx, February 1980 (Box 2)
  - Ekphrasis 1.2, 1997-1998 (Box 2)
  - Verse and Universe: Poems About Science and Mathematics, 1998 (Box 2)
  - Voices from the River, 1990 (Box 2)
  - American Letters and Commentary 10, 1998 (Box 2)
  - American Letters and Commentary 12, 2000 (Box 2)
  - American Letters and Commentary 13, 2001 (Box 2)
  - Notre Dame Review 11, Winter 2001 (Box 2)
  - Notre Dame Review 12, Summer 2001 (Box 2)
  - Jubilat 4, 2002 (Box 2)
  - How Shall We Tell Each Other of the Past? The Life and Writings of Muriel Rukeyser, 1999 (Box 2)
  - Search And You Will Find, 1998 (Box 2)
  - NC 2, 2003 (Box 2)
  - Songs for Our Voices, 1993 (Box 2)
  - The Muse Strikes Back, 1997 (Box 2)
  - Open Door (Poet Love Anthology), 1999 (Box 2)
  - The Little Magazine 16, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Best of Prairie Schooner, 2001 (Box 2)
  - The Breast: An Anthology, 1995 (Box 3)
  - Divided Again: Poems About Designing People, 1999 (Box 3)
  - Columbia Poetry Review 18, Spring 2005 (Box 3)
  - Strange Attractors: Poems of Love and Mathematics, 2008 (Box 3)
  - Atomic Ghost: Poets Respond to the Nuclear Age, 1995 (Box 3)
  - New Poetry: The Extraordinary Tide by American Women, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Lit 2, Winter 2000 (Box 3)
  - The American Voice 12, Fall 1988 (Box 3)
  - The American Voice 21, Winter 1990 (Box 3)
  - In a Field of Words: A Creative Writing Text, 2003 (Box 3)
  - Conditions 7, 1981 (Box 3)
  - Fence 2.1, 1999 (Box 3)
  - New Virginia Review 6, 1988 (Box 3)
  - New Virginia Review 9.1, 1992 (Box 3)
  - Bellingham Review 19.1, 1996 (Box 3)
  - Notre Dame Review 2, Summer 1996 (Box 3)
  - Many Mountains Moving 8.1, 2007-2008 (Box 3)
  - Lumina, 2003 (Box 3)
  - Columbia 3, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Image 23, Summer 1999 (Box 3)
  - Image 31, Summer 2001 (Box 3)
  - Meridian 6, Fall 2000 (Box 3)
  - Mid-Atlantic Review 23.1, 2002 (Box 3)
  - Looking for Home: Women Writing About Exile, 1990 (Box 3)
  - The Measured Word: On Poetry and Science, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Doubletake 2.4, Fall 1996 (Box 3)
  - Croton Review 7, 1984 (Box 3)
  - 5:AM, Winter 1988 (Box 3)
  - Black Buzzard Review 1, 1988 (Box 3)
- Accession (2009-0172), (5 boxes)
  The accession (2009-0172) (700 items; 3.0 lin. ft.; dated 1950s-2009) includes programs and posters from Strickland's publications and performances; school materials from grade school to graduate school; articles and anthologies; electronic media (removed); videotapes; and other miscellaneous materials.
  - TechnoPoetry Festival symposiums 1-3 videotapes, 2002 (Box 4)
  - Eastgate Systems guides (Box 4)
  - True North materials (Box 4)
  - TechnoPoetry Festival materials, 2002 (Box 4)
  - Susanne Shimak thesis (Box 4)
  - New Media and Literature syllabus and materials (Box 5)
  - Multimedia Boot Camp (Box 5)
  - Convergence Conference, 1994 (Box 5)
  - ISAMA proceedings, 2009 (Box 5)
  - Marble Springs, by Deena Larson (teaching materials, correspondence, text) (Box 5)
  - Cyberpoets Guide to Virtual Culture, by John Frost (Box 5)
  - Internet Poetry Sources notebook, 1995 (Box 5)
  - Link structure for To Be Here as Stone Is (Box 5)
  - True North workbook and links (Box 5)
  - Publisher materials (Box 5)
  - Hyperpoetry articles by Stephanie Strickland and others (Box 5)
  - Walls That Were a Garden (Box 5)
  - Correspondence and ephemera (including souvenir ID cards) (Box 5)
  - Schoolwork (Box 6)
  - College notes, 1960s (Box 6)
  - Graduate work: Pratt, Sarah Lawrence (Box 6)
  - Programs, articles, brochures, leaflets, 1980s-1990s (Box 6)
  - Ballad of Sand and Harry Soot (Box 6)
  - Awards and ceremony programs, 1990s-2001 (Box 6)
  - Book covers (Box 6)
  - Errand Upon Which We Came (Box 6)
  - Programs, posters, letters, announcements, photographs (Box 6)
  - Salt Hill (6) bound volume (Box 6)
  - Grand Street bound volume (Box 6)
  - Publications (Box 7)
  - Strickland's resume/CV, 2009 (Box 7)
  - Diplomas (Box 7)
  - 1 Rubix cube poem by a student (Box 7)
  - Interview with Authors, guest: Stephanie Strickland, videotape, 1992, Mar. 25 (Box 7)
    Use Copies: DVD use copy available
  - Denise Duhamel and Stephanie Strickland poetry reading, videotape 1997, Oct. 22 (Box 7)
  - Euclid, Slow.Time, and Knoebel, videotape, 1999 (Box 7)
  - 8 bound volumes (Box 7)
  - Harvard diploma (Box 8)
  - Program/exhibit posters (Box 8)
  - Volume of calligraphy of Strickland poems by Kevin Honan, circa 1990s (Box 8)
- Accession (2009-0195), 1955-2008, (2 boxes)
  The accession (2009-0195) (700 items; 1.2 lin. ft.; dated 1950s-2008) includes files, proofs, and drafts from Strickland's V: Vniverse, True North, Zone: Zero, Red Virgin, Give the Body Back, etc., along with some high school materials, cassette tapes, and a videotape.
  This accession has not been processed, but folders arrived numbered. That schema has been reflected below with Strickland's descriptions of each folder's content.
  - Folder of V: Vniverse source materials; visual sources and inspiration; notes and correspondence from 2000 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - V: Vniverse correspondence and initial notes (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - V: Vniverse constellations; some materials about generative version (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Give the Body Back early materials, reactions; MFA thesis evaluation (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - V: Wave Son.nets/Losing L'una proofs, 2002 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - V: Wave Son.nets/Losing L'una third proof, 2002 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - True North proof and other materials (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Red Virgin quote sources, in order (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - The Red Virgin commentary and reviews (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Proceedings of the CyberMountain Colloquium (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Zone: Zero proof, 2007 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Zone: Zero final proof, 2007 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - V: Wave Son.nets/Losing L'una proofs; Reader's Report and other reviews and interviews (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Vniverse installation plans: never executed (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - High school papers (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Assorted miscellany, including some early e-conferences programs and ISAMA 2009 program (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - P-Queue issue (Box 10)
  - 2 small Press Center audiocassettes from radio broadcasts (Give Body Back and Red Virgin) (Box 10)
  - Labor and Women audiocassette, 1993 (Box 10)
  - Sisyphus Ho videotape (for Ballad of Sand and Harry Soot), 1999 (Box 10)
  - 2 audiocassettes: appearances on To the Best of Our Knowledge, Wisconsin public radio, to talk about Simone Weil, 1993, Aug. 25 and 1993, Dec. 27 (Box 10)
    Use Copies: CD use copies available
- Accession (2009-0267), 1959-2009, (2 boxes)
  The accession (2009-0267) (700 items; 1.2 lin. ft.; dated 1959-2009) includes college papers and essays from her time at Harvard; source materials from works such as Zone: Zero, True North, Sand Soot, and Vniverse; conference programs; journals; and gallery catalogs and other sources used in her work.
  [Preservation reformatting of some college papers may be required before use by researchers.]
  - College papers, Harvard, Fall 1959-Spring 1963 (3 folders) (Box 11)
  - Gallery catalogs that influenced Strickland's work, 1988-1989 (Box 11)
  - YLEM, 1998-2007 (not a complete set) (Box 11)
  - Volt, 2008-2009 (Box 11)
  - Experimental Literary Education, 2009 (Box 11)
  - Montfort Rettberg, Implementation project (Box 11)
  - Edwin Barlow (high school calculus teacher) article (Box 11)
  - Adrienne Dodt thesis on Strickland, 2009 (Box 11)
  - Bound volumes
    - The Measured Word, edited by Kurt Brown (Box 11)
    - WSQ: Technologies, 2009 (Box 11)
    - P-Queue, 2009 (Box 11)
  - &Now Awards, 2009 (Box 12)
  - Jaishree K. Odin interview versions about True North and V, 2002 (Box 12)
  - Reviews and publicity, 2002-2009 (Box 12)
  - Conferences
    - TP21CL pieces, 1999 (Box 12)
    - Digital Arts and Culture, 2000-2001 (Box 12)
    - Society for Literature and Science, 2003-2004 (Box 12)
    - &Now, 2009 (Box 12)
    - ePoetry, Barcelona, 2009 (Box 12)
  - Writings and works
    - Writing from the Workplace, 1995 (Box 12)
    - Text One Zero, 2001 (Box 12)
    - Source materials for slippingglimpse (Box 12)
    - NEH Seminar and True North, 1995-1997 (2 folders) (Box 12)
    - Zero: Zero source and marketing materials (Box 12)
    - Vniverse working materials (Box 12)
    - Sand Soot materials (Box 12)
- Accession (2009-0271), (2 DVDs)
  This small accession consists of a 2-DVD set of Humans, by David Daniels. It has been removed from the collection and cataloged separately.
- Accession (2011-0171), 1970s-2012, (6 boxes, 1 oversize folder)
  The accession (2011-0171) (2250 items; 3.0 lin. ft.; dated 1970s-2012) includes notes, drafts and variants of works such as True North, The Red Virgin, V: WaveSon.nets/Losing L'una, and other Strickland poems, essays, and compilations. Also includes a small amount of correspondence and event material. Electronic media has been separated from the accession and housed on Duke's electronic records server.
  - Writings (Box 13)
    - True North
      - So Far From Home... (early version of True North) (Box 13)
      - Notebooks, 1986 and undated (Box 13)
      - Drafts, 1987-1988, (2 folders) (Box 13)
      - Drafts, from RV binder, (2 folders) (Box 13)
      - Draft, 1987 (early version with plans) (Box 13)
      - Variant, July 1988, (2 folders) (Box 14)
      - Organization notes and spec sheets (Box 14)
    - V: WaveSon.nets/Losing L'una (Box 14)
      - WaveSon.nets/MacDowell long scroll printouts, August 12 and 15, 1997 (Box 14)
      - WaveSon.nets/MacDowell printouts, August 28, 1997 (Box 14)
      - The Woman Who Cannot Do Without (early L'una draft) (Box 14)
      - Saying Simone/Simone Says (early L'una draft) (Box 14)
      - Saying Simone (early Losing L'una), April-June 1997 (Box 14)
    - There is a Woman in a Conical Hat (Box 15)
      - Draft, December 16, 1997 (Box 15)
      - Draft, July 6, 1998 (Box 15)
      - Draft, June 1999 (Box 15)
      - Drafts (Box 15)
    - "V": includes Losing L'una and There is a Woman in a Conical Hat (Box 15)
    - Various drafts, (2 folders) (Box 15)
      Including True North and V: WaveSon.nets/Losing L'una variations, as well as student work.
    - Various drafts from binder (Box 15)
    - Conversation Between Women draft (Box 15)
    - The Birds draft (Box 15)
    - Untitled draft about apples (Box 16)
    - To Be Here as Stone Is drafts (Box 16)
    - Flame-Retention Head draft (Box 16)
    - Give the Body Back (Box 16)
      - Milk in Glass Bottles draft (early version of Give the Body Back) (Box 16)
      - Milk in Glass Bottles draft (Box 16)
      - The Fault of the Body draft with edits (Box 16)
      - The Fault of the Body MFA thesis (Box 16)
      - Living on Air (early version of Give the Body Back) (Box 16)
      - Galleys, 1991 (Box 16)
    - The Red Virgin: A Poem of Simone Weil (Box 17)
      - Notes, 1978-1982 (Box 17)
      - The Simone Weil Poem draft with edits, 1985 (Box 17)
      - The Simone Weil Poem bound draft, 1985 (Box 17)
      - The Only Rival: Simone Weil drafts, (3 folders) (Box 17)
      - The Truth Which Bites: Simone Weil draft and correspondence, 1989-1994 (Box 17)
      - The Red Virgin: A Poem of Simone Weil (bound version), 1993 (Box 17)
    - Essays, Speeches, Presentations (Box 17)
      - Writing the Hungry Body: The Red Virgin paper, April 1997 (Box 17)
      - Hypertext for Poets essays, etc., 1995 (Box 18)
      - Poetry in Transition: The Electronic Word essays, etc., 1995 (Box 18)
      - Women's Biography Seminar, 1997 (Box 18)
      - Moving Through Me as I Move version of talk, 2001-2002 (Box 18)
      - Making the Vniverse, 2003 (Box 18)
      - People's Poetry Panel talks, April 2003 (Box 18)
  - Correspondence (Box 18)
    - Assorted, 1984-2001 (Box 18)
    - Joe Tabbi, re: True North, 1998 (Box 18)
    - Cynthia Lawson, 2003-2004 (Box 18)
  - Events and Publicity (Box 18)
    - Events and organization handouts, 2000-2011 (Box 18)
    - Event programs, 2009-2012 (Box 18)
    - Student work from Georgia Institute of Technology's TechnoPoetry Festival, 2002 (Box 18)
    - Visionary Landscapes participants, 2008 (Box 18)
    - Personal mementoes, undated (Box 18)
    - Various book reviews (Box 18)
  - Journals and Publications (Box 18)
    - Beyond This Silence chapbook, 1985 (Box 18)
    - Dandelion Magazine: The Mapping Issue, 37.1 (Box 18)
    - Ironwood 25, 1985 (Box 18)
    - Western Humanities Review 65.2, Summer 2011 (Box 18)
    - 1913 A Journal of Forms 3, 2009 (Box 18)
  - Posters (Opaperfolder 1)
- Accession (2012-0185), 1986-2012, (1 box)
  Writings by Stephanie Strickland as well as journal appearances and events she has participated in. Also, pieces of work written by authors about Strickland, posters of events, and artwork.
  - Works by Others (Box 19)
    - Raine Koskimaa thesis, 2000 (Box 19)
    - Deena Larsen thesis, 1986 (Box 19)
    - Catalog Codings, 2012 (Box 19)
    - Papers written by Marjorie Luesebrink (Box 19)
    - Letters from Kate Hayles to Howard Foundation, 2003 (Box 18)
    - Howard Foundation Application: Print, also disk (Box 19)
    - Razor Smile 2, 2003 (Box 19)
    - Hyper Text by Odin (Box 19)
    - Materia Sztuki by Ostrowicki (Box 19)
  - Writings (Box 19)
    - Journals (Box 19)
      - Vlak 1.1, 2010 (Box 19)
      - Notre Dame review: The First Ten Years, 2009 (Box 19)
      - Rhythm of Structure, 2011 (Box 19)
      - Dandelion Mapping 37.1, 2011 (Box 19)
      - Barrow Street, 2011-2012 (Box 19)
      - Chicago Review 56:2/3, 2011 (Box 19)
      - Dandelion v.36, Chapter 1&2 (Box 19)
      - Zoland Poetry, no. 5, 2011 (Box 19)
      - Western Humanities Review, v.65 no.2, Summer 2012 (Box 19)
      - American Book Review v.32 no.6, 2011 (Box 19)
    - Readings, Conferences, and Lectures (Box 19)
      - The Kitchen Reading, 2011 (Box 19)
      - Electronic Reading Exhibit, MLA 2012 (Box 19)
      - Poster: Reading with Judd Morrissey (Box 19)
      - Electronic Literature Organization Conference, 2012 (Box 19)
      - Program for Bridges, 2012 (Box 19)
      - & Now Program, 2011 (Box 19)
      - Simone Weil: Dream of Grace in the Gravity of Contemporary Society (Box 19)
      - Interrupt Program, 2012 (Box 19)
      - Grand Valley Writers Series, 2011 (Box 19)
      - Electronic Literature Collection v.2 (Box 19)
    - Books (Box 19)
      - A chapter written in: A Broken Thing (Box 19)
  - Artwork (Box 19)
    - "Stand Under," 2009 (Box 19)